<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gladius justitiae, a sermon preached at the assizes held at Lincoln, March 9, 1667/8 William Welby, esq. being Sheriff of the County / by G.H. M.A.</title>
            <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11810974</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11810974</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 495:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gladius justitiae, a sermon preached at the assizes held at Lincoln, March 9, 1667/8 William Welby, esq. being Sheriff of the County / by G.H. M.A.</title>
                  <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid for Nathaniel Brook,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Gregory Haskard.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gladius Juſtitiae: A SERMON Preached at the ASSIZES held at LINCOLN, <hi>March</hi> 9. 1667/8 WILLIAM WELBY, <abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr> Being Sheriff of the County.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. H.</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <p>Magnificentius eſt dicere, quemadmodum geſſerimus conſulatum quàm quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum ceperimus.</p>
               <bibl>Tully.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Godbid,</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Brook</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Greſham Colledge,</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To His Moſt Honoured Friend</hi> William Welby ESQUIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR this ſmall Piece to crave your countenance, or the making Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies on its behalf (which calls indeed for the <hi>Poſſe Comitatus,</hi> the whole extent of your Office, to defend its weakneſs againſt the attempt of Tongues, which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb facs="tcp:49509:4"/>fiercely to charge it with conceit and confidence,) is unfaithfully to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray you into the ſame cenſure and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. Give me only leave to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon You an impartial Witneſs, not ſuborn'd by affection, to atteſt this Truth; That it was not an itch of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venile years, deſirous to be ſcracht by Popularity; or only an earneſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Friends, the cuſtomary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Scriblers: but direct Commands and friendly threats of the Grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, (whoſe Perſons and Judgements ſave in this, may juſtly challenge a large eſteem and value,) forc'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted a Promiſe of committing this to publick View. So that I diſown to be ſtyl'd the Parent of this haſty birth, let it call Twelve its Father, and be laid at their Door. I can now triumph
<pb facs="tcp:49509:4"/>in an innocent revenge, when I can juſtly indite and call every one of them a <hi>felo de ſe,</hi> for offering violence to his own Judgement, and committing a Rape and Deflowring that modeſty which I account the inviolable duty of my low conceptions, and well becomes the cleareſt intellectuals and beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, which like the greateſt beauty ſhould wear a Vail; for expos'd to Sun and Air to publick appearances to be read by all; they ſoil their Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Complexion, and gain the name of confident. To eſcape ſo black a brand, let me rather confute my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, perſwade You to be a partial Judge, let Your Affections bribe Your Reaſon; or let Me beg me favour of Your Place and Charge, reprieve Me being found Guilty and Condemnd,
<pb facs="tcp:49509:5"/>and account this pure Obedience to their Commands, and a faint return to Your high Civilities and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments laid upon</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble and oblieged Servant, GREGORY HASKARD.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 9th. 1667.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49509:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Romans 13.4.</bibl>
               <q xml:lang="grc">—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</q>
               <q>—For be beareth not the Sword in vain.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Proſelytes betimes had ſuckt in this rotten Principle,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13</note> that Chriſtian Religion did diſcharge all its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors from obedience unto Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Powers,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.19.</note> becauſe it did entitle them to Diadems above,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.16.</note> and ſtyl'd them Co-Heirs with the King of Glory, and endowed them with other fair Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Royalties Divine, they ſtretcht theſe beyond the bounds of a Spiritual deſign, to reach at a Temporal Intereſt; which was to inlarge their Secular liberties to throw open all incloſures, to level Dignities and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, to pluck up the pale of Humane Laws, and tumble down all Supremes, and Saint and Subject no more than King and Rebel could agree. The Apoſtle to diſlodge and prevent this peſtilential opinion, ſo great a rub to the ſpreading of Chriſtianity in the Pagan World, as though Kings muſt then throw off their Purples, when their People put on Chriſts white Robe;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.</note> or ceaſe to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49509:6"/>be God's annointed with his holy Oyl, when their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects foreheads are once ſprinkled with Baptiſmal water, to purge ſo foul a ſtain as this from ſo pure and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent a Religion, and to ſet the Lawrels of Kings faſter upon their brows, to their External power he adjoyns a Divine Commiſſion, their Authority is a bright as their Diadems, their Jewels belong to the new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and ſent by the King above to be Enamel'd in them;<note place="margin">1 King. 10.20.</note> their Thrones more than <hi>Solomon</hi>'s are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> not only to intreat, but command obedience from the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Chriſtians. So that this new proſelyte miſtook his Liberty, and his Religion too, in thinking he ceas't to be a Subject, a Man reduc't into order when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Chriſtian; or to pay Tribute here below to Princes, and Devotion to the King above, could not ſtand together. He therefore gives him this wholſom caution, that if he fall under the laſh and ſtroaks of Civil Government and Juſtice, he muſt not murmure at, and revile, beſpatter and blaſpheme the arm of him that ſtrikes; but kiſs the rod, and pray for the hand of him that holds it,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>O King live for ever,</hi> be patient and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive to His Authority which came from the broad Seal above, and enſtampt with an Image Divine, the Author of His Dignity and Power, as well as of your Religion; For He is the Miniſter of God, <hi>and beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words are included theſe Two parts. (1.) A Character Royal, a Power dirived from God, and delegated unto Judges, or the Authority of Magiſtrates (whereof the Sword is an Enſign) by Letters Patents from the Court above, and ſent down to lower Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49509:6"/>
            <p> Secondly, The deſign and end by a negative, <hi>Non temere,</hi> the Secular arm muſt not wield it furiouſly and raſhly, or uſe it indiſcriminately like the arrows of Death and Famines, making no difference; but muſt point it at the bad and nocent, and protect the good and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Original and Family of the Magiſtrates power. God to tell the World it was not Pride and Ambition, Tyranny, and private Intereſt that firſt erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Polities, and founded the different ſort of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath ſigned their Commiſſion from above, ſent them down inſtruments of Authority, to back and countenance their juſt procedures and execution of Laws, that the Rebel World might not degrade and vilifie their Perſons, ſtyling them poor Mortals, Sons of Earth, caſt in the ſame mould with all Mankind; He hath advanced them to be his Deputies and Vicars, and now they ſound infinite and immenſe in their Authority all Divine deſcending from above, and the Rebellion rebounds from Earth, and toucheth the Throne of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. 'Tis more than Poetry what <hi>Phoebus</hi> told his raſh Son, begging the rule of his Father's Chariot,<note place="margin">Ovid. Metamor.</note> 
               <hi>Non est mortale quod optas;</hi> their ſhoulders had need be more than mortal, who can <hi>canvaſs</hi> for rule of an Immortal concern. Hence refuſal of Supremes, and diſobedience to their Edicts and Commands,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7.</note> like perſecution of Saints and Favorites of Heaven, reflects upon the perſon of God himſelf.<note place="margin">Exod. 16.8.</note> For they have not rejected thee but they have rejected Me; all Government in this ſenſe as well as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> might be called a Theocracy. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and precepts of Kings have a deeper power than only upon the Externals of Men, they reach farther,<note place="margin">Saunder. de obli. Conſci.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49509:7"/>and tie his Conſcience too by this general and deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power from God, who only hath <hi>merum &amp; directum imperium in conſcientias,</hi> an independent unlimited rule. The criminal and diſobedient upon this ſcore miſtake themſelves, becauſe their bodies have ſuffered the penalty and mulcts of Laws, to call their Souls innocent and ſet them clear, their Conſciences ſtill ſtand arraigned at an higher Bar; only Faith and repentance muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that guilt. Hence things of a middle and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different nature, the <hi>Amphibions</hi> in Morals by the commands of Princes, become the matter of neceſſary obedience; and things intrinſecally and materially good, ſeconded with the injunctions of Magiſtrates, lay double chains, and tie the Conſcience faſter; and diſobedience and Rebellion againſt the ſmalleſt Law,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.23.</note> is grim'd with the name of Witchcraft, and Apoſtacy from God, or his Deputy which ſounds the ſame. To ſilence factious and turbulent Spirits, and ſtill the complaints and brawls of unreaſonable Men, before the Judge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict his puniſhments, or diſtribute rewards, let him read his Commiſſion, every Magiſtrate ('tis no invading of Royalty to ſay) is by the Grace of God, his Power is given him from above.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Its deſign and end. All Enſigns and badges of Honour were contrived to repreſent and re-mind their duty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seiden.</hi> Tit. Honour.</note> like Coats of Arms the office and virtue of the bearer; among which the Sword ſignifies an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Juſtice and execution of Laws. For Edicts and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſound but Rhetorick and Oratory, or Formalities of State, painted Weapons, or dead Mens breath, and caſt contempt, light and low thoughts upon the Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power, if their penaltyes and mulcts annext, retch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49509:7"/>not the bold tranſgreſſour and diſobedient; or by wit and intereſt, connivance or relation, can be evaded or compounded at a cheap and inconſiderable rate. Laws of old were therefore written in Stone and Braſs, that their executioners might not be of a ſoft and looſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lubin.</hi> in Juvenal &amp; Perſius.</note> and with <hi>Cinnabaris</hi> or <hi>Rubric, ut immorigeris ſanguineum quid minitarent,</hi> threatning the bloud of him that durſt commit a Rape upon them, and painted out a Spirit bold and unconcerned what the reſult and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion might be of an Office faithfully diſcharged. The definition of a Law by the <hi>Pagan</hi> Orator takes in its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and deſign too,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> 
               <hi>Lex eſt nil aliud niſi recta &amp; à nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Deorum tractata ratio, imperans honeſta, prohibens contraria.</hi> Right reaſon handed down from God to his Officers here below to ſmile upon virtuous and ingenuous, to check and reſtrain ſordid and exorbitant actions. He that prodigally beſtows his pardons and reprieves to Criminals and Malefactors to gain the title of mild and merciful, purchaſeth at the ſame time the name of time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and careleſs, tame and remiſs; his pity becomes a cruelty, while ſeverity to reform, is Mercy only in a ſanguin dreſs. 'Tis the method of Divine Providence to diſplay the lightning of his Love and Charity, the groans of his Spirit, promiſes, and rewards, and other endearments and invitations unto repentance, before he diſcharge the Thunder of his Juſtice, deſpair and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightments, to rend and tear the cauteriz'd Conſcience, and impenitent Soul. Since the World is grown ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident and preſumptuous and lull'd aſleep not to be wak't, or drawn by Love or Mercy the bands of a Man unto obedience, He hath armed his Juſtice with Swords and Arrows, to drive and terrify into a ſober life; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49509:8"/>hath left a model for the Magiſtrates rule, where equity of the Law, dictates of Reaſon and Conſcience, with the cryes of Religion will not reclaim, frowns and angry brows and hands arm'd with the Sword of Juſtice, muſt force, at leaſt diſcourage habitual offenders; <hi>For he carries not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Text thus divided, will return into its ſelf, and frame this Propoſition. <hi>That the ſolemn deſign of all ſorts of Magiſtracy is to protect the good and innocent, and inflict juſt and due puniſhments upon all offenders.</hi> As none of the deſigns and commands of Heaven, as the not eating of an Apple, thoughts and glances, without a blaſphemy, can be thought indifferent and low, much leſs his inauguration of Kings and Magiſtrates, his Deputies and Vicegerents, by which he rules this lower World. Diſpenſation of Law and Juſtice was contrived, not like the badges and glittering marks of Honour to diſtinguiſh degrees and ſubordinate files of Men, to make the vulgar World only to gaze and pay reverence to their purples: but to fulfil that ſolemn deſign and end which Heaven its ſelf with all its Rhetorick, HOly policies, Divine and Moral arguments, would joyfully perſwade; which is the curbing of all Irregularity, to civilize the barbarous World, to diſgarriſon Vice and Injuſtice, Fraud and Oppreſſion, to make the World purely Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;<note place="margin">Iſai. 11.16.</note> when the Lyon and the Lamb, the Vulture and the Dove, the weaker and the ſtronger Chriſtian, ſhould live, love, and lie down together. So that that which is the Ruler's Charge, is the care of Heaven, and the Miniſtry of Angels, they being ſtyl'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and are diſpatcht into this lower World upon the meſſages of the upper one,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> to infuſe Holy thoughts, and Divine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49509:8"/>tempers, which carry on the Ruler's Office to advance Virtue and Religion, and reclaim the degenerate world. His thoughts are therefore too courſe and vulgar which ſtyles them purely Humane,<note place="margin">Verſe. 1.</note> when Heaven hath cloath'd them in Divinity; and gives too favourable a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſobedience, which charges it only with a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral mulct,<note place="margin">Verſe 2.</note> when my Apoſtle paſſes an eternal doom upon it. When therefore you are inſtal'd God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roys, the Champions of Religion, the Patrons of Virtue, the expectation and hopes of all good Men,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> the Terror of the bad, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the walking Law; think not ſo low and humbly, the Adminiſtration of Juſtice to be a thing only Gentile and Titular, of a Secular Intereſt and convenience, and looks below; entertain more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and noble conceptions, and look upon your Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of an higher deſign, an Immortal concern, the ſtate beyond the Grave, into which all the ſmaller and the large lines of this life and its actions, muſt all at laſt reſolve and centre themſelves. To fix this burthen and care faſter upon your ſhoulders, conſider and weigh theſe enſuing obligations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The neceſſity of Humane Nature. Since Man lapſt into this degenerate condition, and Sin became his Maſter, his Nature now is no more led by Love and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, but by the ſeverities of Juſtice laſht into a ſober and coverſive life. For the paſſions and rage of the general part of Mankind will no more be boyled over, and cool'd by rational arguments and out of principles of Virtue, than the lowd and ſurly ſtorm can be allayed and ſeren'd by ſtrains of Rhetorick or gentile deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that Humane Nature being ſo feſter'd and gangren'd, grown ſo rough and ſturdy, it calls for cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and lancings, more than lenitives and remulcients,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49509:9"/>Laws and penalties from the ſharpeſt Sword of Juſtice. So that paint but the World as once it lay in its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chaos and confuſion, <hi>Figida cum calidis,</hi> &amp;c. Draw the diſmal conſequences of Civil Warrs, Inroads of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes and depopulations, ſecret Murders, and open In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſions, with all the numerous ſpawn of miſchiefs, you will then diſcern what a deformed monſter this World would turn, if inſtead of wholſom Laws, and an exact diſtribution of Juſtice, with a free, a cheerful obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the harmony of the moral World, only the harſh notes of tyrany and oppreſſion, frauds and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſhould grate upon your ears; the tears of Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and the cryes of Orphans; the deaths of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, and blood of all good Men; no ſitting under our Vines to crop their fruit, though watred with the ſweat of our own brows, or calling for Land-marks of propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, when life it ſelf would not be our own, but Tenant at Will to anothers paſſion &amp; revenges; the ſtrongeſt arm would be the greateſt right; the weakeſt Chriſtian the greateſt criminal; ſubtilty would be Juſtice; and want of power with the groans of the poor, the only crying vice. Reaſon and Religion, candour and ingenuity, with all the lovely principles of humane nature, would lie a bleeding, and a <hi>fiat juſtitia modò ruat Coelum</hi> might rather have this ſenſe, Heaven would totter if Juſtice were not done. For theſe and many more, like the opening of <hi>Pandora's</hi> box would ſwarm together, if once the ſtreams of Juſtice be obſtructed, penalties remiſsly inflicted upon diſobedience, and the Pale of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venment pluckt up by the brawny hands of violence. So that'a faithful diſpenſer of Juſtice is a benefactor to all Mankind, repairing its ruines, the only <hi>Atlas</hi> of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49509:9"/>moral. World, which otherwiſe would ruſh into Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The Sword of Juſtice therefore like the Angel's flaming one, muſt ſtill guard Paradiſe, Religion, and Equity, leaſt it become a Wilderneſs of <hi>Sin.</hi> The eyes and hopes therefore of all innocen: Souls, the cryes of all good Men, and of our common Parent too for your Protection againſt theſe black and diſmal ills, which are ſo cloſely linkt and twiſted with the corrupt and ruinous nature of Mankind, make your Juſtice of an indiſpenſable convenience and abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider who you repreſent. Your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power like <hi>Janus,</hi> carry a double face; they look upward towards God, who hath choſen you his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and Exarchs in ruling the Provinces of this lower world: and juſt Sentences and Dooms he appropriates, and calls them his own, The Judgement is Gods. And it looks below to the People your fellow Beings, whoſe Truſtees and Repreſentatives you are, to diſtribute the equal ſhares of Juſtice. The one in your Commiſſion ſets you above the level of Mankind;<note place="margin">Deu. 1.17.</note> for what the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious <hi>Pagans</hi> would have enamel'd in their Crowns, as <hi>Domitian</hi> call'd himſelf, <hi>Dominus Deus noſter,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian, ſtill courts the title of <hi>Rome Pagan,</hi> as though entail'd upon her,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Selden.</hi> Tit Honour. Revel. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>Seſoſtris</hi> wrote himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Corrival with the King of Heavens title, <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> with what the <hi>Peruvian</hi> Kings of late, or the <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours now do ſwell, is enjoyed in a ſober and modeſt ſenſe by the Adminiſtrators of Juſtice, when God Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens them with his own name, <hi>I ſay ye are Gods. Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum imperium cum</hi> Jove Caeſar <hi>babet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8:.5.</note> Their Commiſſion being higher than their Crowns, of an immortal race.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49509:10"/>The other ſtyles you Guardians, and Feoffees in truſt, of the Peoples Proprieties and Poſſeſſions. A Judge no longer remains aſingle and individual Perſon, but ſounds a Multitude, a Legion, a Leviathan of Men, a Monopoly of Rights and Priviledges, the Beaſt with many Heads;<note place="margin">Revel. 13.</note> Beaſt in Prophetick Schemes and Types ſignifying Goverment, or Polities. So that the remiſs. Migiſtrate that falls in love with Beauty and Varniſh of his Office like the giddy <hi>Phaeton, currus miratur habenas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> and neglects a ſtrict and wiſe diſcharge, doth not only beſpot his own Purples, but ſhakes the Throne of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven too, from whence his Commiſſion came. If the Judge that is inveſted with the Peoples Rights, miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy or wreſt their Truſt from its firſt intention of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them from the greedy jaws of Rapine and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and abuſe them to crooked deſigns and private Intereſts, he acts in part what <hi>Caligula</hi> wiſht, <hi>that all the World had but one neck, and he its Executioner;</hi> He mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the People with their own Right committed to him. Private perſons like ſmaller Stars may be obſeur'd, and no dammage to the lower World; but Publick like Sun or Moon when once Eclipſt, Heaven and Earth ſeem to mourn in blackneſs, with a train of aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating circumſtances. Hence then to make your Office anſwer its Pedigre and Original which is Divine, Gods. Commiſſioners, and the Peoples Truſt, impartially and deveoid of Fear, inflict due puniſhments upon Offenders, <hi>and uſe not the Sword in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let the Magiſtrate conſider the grand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at an higher Bar. God to over-aw the actions of Mankind, and ſtrike a Reverence into mortals breaſts, hath plac'd himſelf a ſpectator and Judge at lower Bars,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49509:10"/>good and bad Angels more then <hi>Mahomets</hi> upon the two ſhoulders of every Diſciple, to record your Sentences, and the Mind and Conſcience of all good Men, the grand Inqueſt at the laſt Tribunal, where all Cauſes muſt be tryed ore and pleaded once again, the Court of Equity the laſt appeal; where all unjuſt damages, too rigid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, paſſionate Dooms and Sentences, and deciſions of deſign, will wheel about, and return upon the Judges ſcore. The cries of the weak and deſtitute, whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty here below was their only crime, and the blood of Martyr'd Innocents reeks up to Heaven, and returns in a ſhower of Vengeance or the Thunder of Conſcience upon the drowzy Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Acts 18.27.</note> who like <hi>Gallio</hi> was a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator of Riots and Injuſtice, yet cared for none of thoſe. The Judge therefore, that only admires the ſplendor of his Office, and courts the Pomp, and Retinue of his Charge, the noiſe of his Duty, without regard to the Lines of Juſtice, Laws of Equity, and proportions of Reaſon, dies like <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> in beds of Roſes, the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pleaſure of his Office to delight his Senſes, yet forgets the Aſp upon her breaſt the ſting of Conſcience there. Every Man hath numerous ſwarms of his own Sins, and may read large Catalogues of his private Crimes, enough to put his Soul in a ſweat and agony; but Men of publick capacities, to have the Sins of Cities and Villages, Nobles and Plebeians, all where he reformed not nor diſtributed right, charg'd upon their account, ſtands in need of the back of Angels, the brawny Conſciences of Fiends, the Lethargy and ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity of the deſperate to bear ſo great a load. Sins and Crimes of People and Magiſtrates are correlatives as well as they, and have been mutually charged upon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49509:11"/>another; and as there is in the body Natural, ſo in the Politick too a Circulation of bloud, and return of ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to infeſt the head; the tranſgreſſion of a People being ſcor'd upon the Supreme, whoſe timidity and ſlackneſs in Reformation, hath given birth and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to many a Vice. He being called the <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> hath entail'd his vices with their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Penalties and Judgements, as well as his Crown and Dignities upon the People, or his Heir apparent. Divine anger and revenge, as well as Sins and Diſeaſes of impenitent Mortals run in the blood.<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.28.</note> If the Magiſtrate therefore will be tender of Sin below, if he dread the Crimes of others more than their Ghoſts to haunt them in this lower World, if he fear to be degraded, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Malefactor at an higher Bar, if he expect the charge of his Five Cities to multiply into a larger power, let him draw the Sword of Juſtice reſolutely, and ſheath it in the bowels of Sin.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let him conſider the great diſcouragement he gives to Virtue. The Magiſtrate whoſe Office calls him the Scourge of Vice, the terrour and affrightment of all exorbitant actions, the Champion of Religion, and Patron of all good Men; if he begin to dye Scarlet Sins of a faint complexion, and ſtyle them Peccadillo's; if fearſul to ſtrike, becauſe the offence came from great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or <hi>grandeur;</hi> or acquits a Criminal without his juſt and deſerved penalty, he turns the Protector of Vice, the oblique Perſecutor of all virtuous and brave actions, the Caterpillar of the Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> the only bane of Religion. For while Men live in this vale of tears, and begirt with this maſs of fleſh; and humour and paſſion are become half, if not the larger, part of the Man,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49509:11"/>they ſooner become Proſelytes to Virtue from Rewards and Puniſhments, then from Internal Principles, or a rational love: the Vail and Shrine recommends <hi>Diana,</hi> while her beauty is inviſible. So that in not inflicting due Puniſhments upon Offenders, Virtue feels the ſmart which they deſerve, and is robb'd of one of her methods to gain Profeſſors, while Vice's Torment becomes Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue's Triumph, and commands our Love and Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therefore <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſaid well,<note place="margin">Xenophon</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. When good Men who do not always ſee by the light of Grace and Reaſon, but through the Spectacles of Senfe and Fancy, ſee Vice diſcountenanc'd and frown'd upon, their appetites are whetted, and carry a keener edge, to proſecute Virtue and Religion ſtill, and advance its practice. Though he that takes his Religion only upon the ſcore of priviledges and immunities, rewards and praiſes that attend it, and no more, is but a Sales-man in Religion, and a Mercenary in Devotion; or he that lives a virtuous life for fear of whipps and laſhes, the ſtrokes of Juſtice and ſeverity, that ought to be the companion of his Vice, may be call'd God's ſlave, and not his ſervant; his vaſſal, not his Son, the title of the pious.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe may be good motives and arguments at 'firſt, but not the Principle and <hi>Baſis</hi> to bottom our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion on. So that a remiſs and timerous Magiſtrate in deducting the due penalties from Vice, ſtifles Religion in the Cradle, hinders that which might have been the firſt ſtep to a regenerate life; many have been ſcar'd and terrified into a Divine converſation, by the ſtrange dooms, and unexpected diſmal providences, more than the dreams of Hell, that have ſeiz'd upon unrepenting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49509:12"/>Sinners. Virtue therefore throws her ſelf at your feet, Religion is your Supplicant, and all good Men cry for juſt and impartial puniſhments upon, Sin and Vice. Twill augment the Seminaries of Virtue; 'Twill weed out Vice, and lop off all luxuriant actions; 'Twill gloſs upon your Honour, and make your Sword ſhine the brighter.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Conſider what ill example it will prove unto the World of returning acts of injuſtice upon them that are unjuſt in their diſcharge. For the World that loves revenge and retaliation of wrongs, will catch at all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of reflecting back the ſame,<note place="margin">Amos 6.12</note> or greater inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon him which hath been unjuſt before. When therefore Rule degenerates into Tyranny, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into Hemlock, and Bribery, (or by a ſofter name preſenting) corrupts the ſtreams of Juſtice, when right is meaſured by proportion to their own Intereſt, and others behaviour and carriage towards them, The Crowns of Kings begin to totter, their Scepters ſhake like <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Reeds, and all ſorts of Magiſtracy depend at will and uncertainty, the Subject lying in wait to throw off the yoke of oppreſſion, and disthrone their Government; Anarchy with freedom, then Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Injuſtice being more grateful to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the rabble which naturally ſounds confuſion. For though Chriſtianity, the Spirit of Chriſt did never (like his Antitype <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.54</note>) turn the Rivers into ſtreams of bloud, or call down Fire or Legions of the Spirits above, to defeat his enemies; but commands us pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and a generous temper with ſubmiſſion to unjuſt exactors: yet there is a paſſionate rage and fury in the breaſts of the unregenerate World, which being the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger number, will ſoon pluck down a continual &amp; habitual
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49509:12"/>Injuſtice. But if experience of all Kingdoms, and ſayings of all politick heads, will not evince this truth,<note place="margin">16.10.</note> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the wiſe King in his <hi>Proverbs.</hi> The Throne is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by righteouſneſs, and the dignity of all inferior Magiſtrates coucht under that more general and ſplendid title. An uneven Juſtice like nouriſhment to the body; diſtributed in unequal ſhares, makes ſome limbs Gigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and others Dwarfiſh, and the whole body politick monſtrous and prodigious, and becomes the ſooner ruin'd, being over weak to bear ſo great a load, like <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi>'s ſhoulders upon an Infants legs. This unequal deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Juſtice, and executions of Laws, hath call'd in queſtion the inſtitution of Magiſtracy, queſtioning its Family, tearing its Commiſſion from above, ſtyling it only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a creature of Man's formation,<note place="margin">1 Peter 2.13.</note> a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table convenience and temporary intereſt, and a ſutable obedience is paid to its commands; not out of Conſcience and Religion, but fear and uſefulneſs:<note place="margin">Epheſ.6.6</note> and as theſe do change, ſo will their eye-ſervice too into Rebellion. 'Tis ſhame we ſhould give ſtill life to that aged Proverb which is the death and bane of wholſom Laws, which makes them cobweb-Lawn, to catch and trapan the little animal, but larger ones are above their force; as though weakneſs was the only guilt, and ſtrength was innocency. This hath made the World believe, that Laws and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Juſtice and Right, are nothing elſe but ſtrength and Force, Might and Power; and think the ſame of them, that looſer gallants of Virtue and Religion, only the fancy of ſome brain-ſick Student, the contrivance of a Conclave or Council-board, to reduce Fools and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and credulous Subjects into aw. As though a tame Seal with an imaginary face of Eagles, or Lyons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49509:13"/>Rampant, the ſcar-crowns of Babes upon a piece of harmleſs wax affixt to Parchment, the Coat only of ſome innocent Sheep, ſhould drive away and terrify their rank and rapacious appetites.<note place="margin">Hobs.</note> This made the Leviathan ſay that the ſtare of Nature was a ſtate of War, who feaſts and preys upon the ſmaller fry; Right and Poſſeſſions were only reſignations enforc'd by Might and Power; and the Man beſt arm'd, a <hi>Cap a pe</hi> juſtitiary, like the Scales of a Leviathan,<note place="margin">Daniel 7.</note> was cloath'd with the greateſt Juſtice. Hence Beaſts are well aſſigned the Types and Hieroglyphicks of Rule and Civil Polities; where the fierceſt look, the longeſt paw, and ſharpeſt tooth ſhall call them Princes: the Lyon is call'd King of Beaſts from theſe. If therefore you would put a hook into the noſtril of this Leviathan, if you would underprop the Thrones of King, and fix their Crowns faſter on their Heads, if you expect as 'tis due, Reverence and Honour to be paid unto your Purples, if you would perſwade the World 'tis Reaſon and Religion, Conſcience and Divinity commands, not Strength and force, a <hi>Faſcis</hi> or <hi>Securis,</hi> Swords and Rods, that Enact Laws, diſtribute evenly and impartially Juſtice and Equity unto all.</p>
            <p>This Propoſition being ſo enforc'd, may be applyed to two ſorts, which carry the great concern in Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To thoſe who are only to prepare Cauſes, Complaints and Defenſes,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 31.4.</note> top ripen and mature for the Laws definitive Sentence; like <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour-bearer, to deliver the Sword into the Judges hand for Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Becauſe Judgement and Juſtice muſt be given <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum allegata &amp; probata,</hi> according as things are well alledged, and fairly proved, they are as much to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49509:13"/>reminded of their duty, as he that paſſeth the final Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. There is a numerous ſwarm of Officers in Courts of Juſtice, which like Caterpillars, Flyes and Gnats, and other inſects, only buzz and ſting, raiſe reports and vex Mens names and quiet; and like thoſe of <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſtrive to over-cloud and darken Judgement. The World hath commenc'd in ſo high a degree of Sin, that ſome of its Sons can out-ſwagger their own Conſcience, <hi>Hector</hi> Religion, ſwear and depoſe any thing; the old Greek Proverb fits their mouths, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Lend me Sir an Oath to day in my action, I'le make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſwear for you to morrow.</hi> Some that love to dreſs up a bad cauſe in the embroydery of Rhetorick, the Pictures and Shadows of Oratory to paſs for truth and reality; Some dilight to involve the truth with ſeeming difficulties, and artificial perlexities; Some ſtrive by Demurrs and Procraſtinations, like <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enniu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not ſo much by truth and valour, as by delay, to win the Field; they ſeem to lay Siege to Equity, and would ſtarve out and impoveriſh an innocent Cauſe, by having the fatter or deeper purſe. By ſuch occaſions and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions they endeavour to put out the eye of Juſtice, making it as blind in Reaſon, as it ought to be in Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; dint the Sword of Juſtice, caſt a miſt before the Judges eye, that he might miſtake a right definitive Sentence. And thus ſucceſs in Law ſhall not depend upon Right and Equity, but Chance and Fortune, Croſs and Pile for a Victory. Nothing hath opened the jaws of the black-mouth'd World, to beſpatter more the ingenuous ſtudy of the Law, than this, when the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates and Profeſſors of it, wreſting and perverting <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and end of deciding Controverſies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49509:14"/>compoſing defferences, untying intricacies, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting Right to all, beſtow its force to buoy up a party &amp; factions; to befriend a relation, and oppoſe truth; to ſwell a Fee, and leſſen Conſcience, and by art and skill in ſubtleties and cobweb-Lawns; to caſt a blind; to diſguiſe an unjuſt Cauſe, to make it a proſperous and ſucceſsful one; Who look at this as the grand deſign, the Cauſe was ingeniouſly and wittily pleaded, and as well rewarded; while Innocency and Right, that wanted a ſmooth Tongue, and an open Hand, ſhut up by pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, loſt the day. And thus fetch up Law, and ſeeming Reaſon, dreſt up with de advantages of Rhetorick, and a confident carriage, to deſtroy that Virtue whoſe Guardian and Patron it was firſt deſign'd. 'Tis ſad, yet common, that he ſhould be accounted a guilty perſon or criminal, becauſe he is only ſtoutly accuſed, and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torically charged with Vice; The World knows the Proverb too well, <hi>fortièr acouſa &amp; aliquid adhaerebit;</hi> ſtrike home, and be ſure a Scarr will remain, if the Wound be not Mortal. For 'tis one of the diſmal ills, and largeſt piece of Injuſtice in this life, that if Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and an unſpotted name be once called in queſtion, and arraigned by paſſions and malice, though clearly quitted and well diſcharged, ye jealouſies and ſurmizes ſtill keep their lodgings in cankerd and ill-natur'd breaſts, to which it holds up its hands, and is condemned to ſuffer the private puniſhment of reproach and ſcandal. 'Tis ſad, that when malice and jealouſie, peeviſhneſs and faction ſhall commence a ſuit, that wiſe Laws ſhould be proſtituted by promoting and informing, bribery and a witty tongue, to carry on ſo inhumane and barbarous deſign. It was thereofore well provided by the Ancients,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49509:14"/>as the <hi>Roman</hi> and other Laws to witneſs, that the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſhould firſt depoſe before the <hi>Praetor</hi> before he put in his Libel, that he was free from all malicious and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnious intent. Hence the Magiſtrate had ever a Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude indulg'd to him, and a Power left him to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the letter of the Law, preſt by a croſs-grain'd and litigious nature, and follow the equity and intention of it. They propounded therefore rewards for uſeful and neceſſary Informations, and ſet Fines and Mulcts upon trivial, froward, and ſuperficial ones. Hence the <hi>Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff</hi> and <hi>Defendant</hi> did mutually make a pledge or <hi>depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum,</hi> a certain ſum, if the cauſe was not well prov'd, and as fairly defended, and the puniſhment deſigned for the accuſed party to return upon the Informer or Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff, if once it did appear Malice or Envy had drawn up the Charge. Theſe, and many more, with the Conſent and Reaſon of all good Men, ſhew'd their juſt ſeverity and indignation againſt Sycophants and bribed Orators, raiſing debates, <hi>de Lanacirc; Caprina,</hi> about Air and Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine out of paſſion and malice, catching at niceties and letters, to degrade the gravity of the Law, and caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon ſo well and deſigned functions. Theſe, like other Malefactors and Criminals, deſerve as juſt, if not a larger puniſhment; the one robbing but the Lives and Fortunes of ſingle Men, but theſe commit a Rape, and murder the Law, the defence of all Societies, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind too.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the Magiſtrate or Judge, from whom all Determinations and final Sentences, the reſult and concluſion of all former Oaths and Atteſtations muſt come. Whoſe Authority being ſigned with the broad Seal of Heaven, his Commiſſion from the Throne of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49509:15"/>God, and a Sword put into his Hands, he muſt not let it ſleep in the Scabbard, or make falſe flouriſhes, or only be an ornament by his ſide; but muſt draw it with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Hand, an impartial and unconcern'd Spirit, for execution upon Sin and Vice. We live in the latter times,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.1</note> in a confident and preſumptuous age, when Vice hath gotten a ſteeded brow, when Wickedneſs is become Gentile and Faſhionable, Licentiouſneſs counted Modiſh Education, the ſcurrilous and Blaſphemous Droll cry'd up the ingenuous and witty Man, and well diſguiſed Fraud and Faction eſteemed the Politick head; and theſe muſt be dealt withal as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did with the <hi>Roman Senate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Florus.</note> if his requeſt with their free choice would not create him <hi>Conſul,</hi> his Sword ſhould give the caſting voice for his Election. If Principles of Virtue, Reaſon and Religion, will not reclaim the debauch'd and ſturdy World, Laws and Penalties from the Secular arm muſt drive and beat the World into Obedience. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate then acting like that God he repreſents, who firſt diſplays the lightening of his Love and Charity, to melt the ſoft and plyable Soul, and then diſchargeth the Thunder of his Juſtice to rend and tear impenitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And thus reforming the unregenerate World, and advancing Righteouſneſs and Religion, your Secular Sword turns into that of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.30.</note> and like <hi>Phinehas</hi> you execute Judgement, or Pray at the ſame time. Your Commiſſion being given and made your Duty, all ſorts and Files of injured Men may not only petition and beg, but command your Juſtice and a free acceſs for all. The poor that walks in rags, and dwells in ſmoaking Cottages, may confidently come unconcern'd upon the Equity of his Cauſe. Greatneſs and Riches here are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49509:15"/>falſe Topicks to prove the goodneſs of a Cauſe, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and Poſſeſſions are too ſcant to meaſure the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of the Man, no more than by the ſhaddow of the Body you can take the height of a Soul or Mind. The Souls of rich and poor are Jewels of an equal luſtre, the one is only better ſet, and enamel'd in more flouriſhing eſtate, the other rough and unpoliſht; yet they muſt be valued not ſo much for their accidental gloſſes, as their natural beauty. Noble and <hi>Plebeian</hi> Souls have the Divine Image equally enſtampt upon them; the one only is ſet in a more gilded frame, a more ſplendid condition: yet we reſpect the Picture for its ſtroaks and proper features common to both from God the Carver of Souls; and <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image commands regard, whether in Gold or Braſs, or courſer mettle. The helpleſs Widdow and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Orphan may ſmile at ſuch a Tribunal, where their potent adverſary, with his ſwelling pride, and large retinue, muſt be look'd upon with a diſintereſted and impartial eye; the Judge is deputed the Orphan's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Widdow's Husband to redreſs their wrongs. The ignorant and home-ſpun Man that dreads the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſms of Law and great appearances, may call for the Magiſtrate to be Spectacles for his blear'd eye, Crutches for his decrepit &amp; dejected faculties, who muſt be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make him juſt. <hi>Oculus in Sceptro,</hi> the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Hieroglyphick, beſpoke the duty of a Ruler, the eye of knowledge upon his Scepter, leaſt the brightneſs of the Crown upbraided and inſulted over the dulneſs of the head that wore it. An ignorant Magiſtrate repreſent the blind Man ſteering at the Helm by the Polar Star he yet ne're ſaw; the Pilot then muſt needs turn Pirate, and ſink the Ship of Government. The Magiſtrate would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49509:16"/>do well like the Philoſopher, to put out the eye of Senſe and Affection, to ſee the clearer by the light of Reaſon. The ſtranger or alien <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Fagan</hi> need not be jealous of Friends and Favourites, and different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions; at Altars and Tribunals relations ceaſe, Religion and Conſcience muſt know no Father or Mother. If once Tribunals were ſo adorned, We ſhould recover the times that are paſt, and reſtore the Judges as of old, when Reaſon and Religion, Juſtice and Equity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and an eye to God kept the Chair, and Virtues were the only ſteps by which they did aſcend, and ſat in the Gates,<note place="margin">Deut. 22.15.</note> and gave free invitation for all; and all good Men, and juſt Societies might triumph in the ſame ſtrain with old <hi>Rome</hi> at the choice of <hi>Numa,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Plutarch</note>. When Kings and Judges are virtuous and knowing too, their People receive a King and a Kingdom both. What then remains, but to draw and uſe this Sword with a ſteady and impartial hand, regardleſs of others frowns or ſmiles, or any ſmall events that may attend your Charge, unbyaſſed to Sects and Parties,<note place="margin">1 Kings 22.31.</note> Qualities and Conditions, fight againſt none but Sin and Wickendneſs, Lewdneſs and confident Vice; this will call you truly Man, and God's Deputy; This will ſtyle you Saint, and advance your Temporal Chair into a Spiritual one,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.7.</note> to Judge in the other World at the period of this; This will make you Heir apparent to the Character of a Faithful Steward, and the Rewards of Immortality with the Bleſſed Jeſus, to whom be Honour and Glory, both now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49509:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
